Guide to the John Nolen Papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
Nolen, John papers,1890-1938, 1954-1960.
- Series IV. Professional Career
  - Other Professional Activities, and Public Works
    - Other Public Services, Conferences, Federal Government
      - United States Legislation, 1932 - 1934 (Box 16, Folder 21)
        Correspondence and materials regarding H.R.10748; H.R.1672 & S.J. Res.4 regarding Muscle Shoals and Tennesee Valley. Also lists of US Government from 1933 and 1934.
      - Economic Recovery, 1932 (Box 16, Folder 22)
        A few items regarding place of planning & public works in economic recovery
      - Project Book -- Union Park Gardens, DE, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        Project specs, planting estimates, plans for Union Park Gardens
      - Union Park Gardens -- printed copies, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 2)
        Many printed copies of Union Park Gardens general plan on 8.5 x 11" sheets
      - Land Subdivision Cuts - J.N. Office Plans, 1913 - 1920 (Box 17, Folder 3)
        Multiple printed copies of general plans of: Seneca Heights, Olean, NY; Loveland Farms (Buckeye Land Co., Ohio);Neponset Garden Village, East Walpole, MA; Green Acres, Waterbury, CT; Kestler Industrial Village, Mifflin County, PA.
      - Specific Instructions, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        Recommendations and suggestions regarding town planning/streets and pavements/industrial housing for US Government agencies: US Shipping Board-Emergency Fleet Corporation-Dept of Housing-Div of Production. Also cost estimates. Most dated 1918
      - Project Book: Niagara Falls, NY, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 5)
        Estimate and Data to accompany preliminary plan for Niagara Falls Project (USHC #404)
      - U.S.H.C. Blank Forms (Box 17, Folder 6)
        Blank forms for cost estimating housing developments
      - Project Book: Ridley Park, PA, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 7)
        Materials - reports, numbers, costs - estimates and data relating to Ridley Park preliminary schemes (USHC #2947)
      - Ridley Park, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 8)
        Mostly estimates relating to the Ridley Park project
      - Miscellaneous - Extra copies, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 9)
        Miscellaneous extra copies of cost-estimate forms from various projects
      - Eddystone, PA, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 10)
        Estimates and data to accompany preliminary plan for Eddystone Project (USHC #1635)
      - Project Book: Niagara Falls, NY, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 11)
        Cost estimates, scheduling, plan drawings, instructions relating to Niagara Falls project (USHC #404)
      - Project Book: Eddystone, PA, 1918 (Box 17, Folder 12)
        Cost estimates, scheduling, plan drawings, instructions relating to Eddystone project (USHC #1635)
      - Notes: Services for Gov't Agencies (Box 17, Folder 13)
        Records of hours, charges, payment, etc. for work done for various government agencies. Sorted by agency.
      - Address File, 1927 - 1928 (Box 40, Folder 4)
        For the National Conference on City Planning, 1927
      - National Conference on State Parks, 1933 - 1936 (Box 59, Folder 21)
        Correspondence - state parks
      - National Resources Committee - East Georgia Planning Council, 1936 (Box 61, Folder 1)
        Correspondence - planning for East Georgia
      - (2) National Resources Committee - East Georgia Planning Council, 1936 (Box 61, Folder 2)
        Correspondence and newspaper clippings - planning for East Georgia
      - (3) National Resources Committee - East Georgia Planning Council, 1936 - 1937 (Box 61, Folder 3)
      - Resettlement Administration, 1934 - 1937 (Box 61, Folder 10)
        Correspondence and newspaper clippings - consulting services for Resettlement Administration; policies and initiatives of Resettlment Administration including subsistence homesteads and suburban housing
      - (4) National Resources Board - Vermont State Plan, 1935 (Box 61, Folder 11)
      - National Resources Committee - Vermont State Plan, 1935 (Box 61, Folder 12)
      - (6) National Resources Committee - Vermont State Plan, 1935 (Box 61, Folder 13)
      - (7) National Resources Committee - Vermont State Plan, 1936 (Box 61, Folder 14)
      - (8) National Resources Committee - Vermont State Plan, 1936 (Box 61, Folder 15)
      - National Resources Committee - Vermont State Plan, 1936 (Box 61, Folder 16)
      - Resettlement Administration - Personal Inquiry, 1935 - 1936 (Box 61, Folder 17)
        Correspondence - requests for Nolen's recommendation of former employees seeking work with Resettlement Administration
      - Resettlement Administration - Miscellaneous, 1935 (Box 61, Folder 18)
        Reports, pamphlets, newspaper clippings -Resettlement Administration; Berwyn Heights, MD community development "Tugwelltown"; Subsistence Homesteads
      - Public Works Administration - Housing Administration - Miscellaneous Material, 1935 (Box 61, Folder 19)
        Correspondence, reports, pamphlets, newspaper clippings - federal housing projects
      - Public Works Administration - Housing Administration - Miscellaneous Material, 1935 - 1936 (Box 61, Folder 20)
        Correspondence,reports, newspaper clippings - federal housing projects; two proposed sites in Boston area in South Boston and Cambridge, MA
      - State Planning, 1933 - 1934 (Box 62, Folder 1)
        Correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports, and bulletins - National Resources Board; Public Works Administration; state and regional planning for various states and regions in U.S.
      - Subsistence Homesteading, 1933 (Box 62, Folder 2)
        Correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings - federal Subsistence Homesteads program
      - Subsistence Homesteads, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 3)
      - Subsistence Homesteads, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 4)
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Cumberland, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 5)
        Correspondence and reports - planning of Cumberland Homestead near Crossville, TN
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Delaware, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 6)
        Correspondence and reports - planning of Delaware Homestead in Wilmington, DE
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Hightstown, New Jersey, 1934 - 1935 (Box 62, Folder 7)
        Correspondence and reports - planning of Jersey Homesteads in Hightstown, NJ
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Jasper, Alabama, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 8)
        Correspondence - planning of Jasper Homesteads in Jasper, AL
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Meridian, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 9)
        Correspondence Meridian Homesteads in MS
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Newton's Reports, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 10)
        Correspondence - reports on land planning work in 1934, includes list of homesteads in various states thruout U.S.
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Contract Arrangements for Technical Services, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 11)
        Correspondence and reports - employment of those planning subsistence homesteads
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Tygart Valley, West Virginia, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 12)
        Correspondence, reports and maps - planning of Tygart Valley Homesteads in Elkins, WV
      - Subsistence Farming - Westmoreland County, Pennsylvania, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 13)
        Correspondence and map - planning of Westmoreland Homestead in PA
      - U.S. Department of Commerce Committee - Subdivision Layout, 1931 - 1933 (Box 62, Folder 14)
        Correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports - Committee on Subdivision Layout; The President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Applications for Work, 1934 - 1935 (Box 62, Folder 15)
        Correspondence - recommendations and applications for jobs with Subsistence Homestead projects
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Accounts, 1933 - 1935 (Box 62, Folder 16)
      - U.S. Department of Interior - Pay Roll Section - Mary S. Von Hook, 1934 - 1936 (Box 62, Folder 17)
        Correspondence - payment for services rendered and expenses for Division of Subsistence Homesteads,National Resources Committee, National Park Service and Department of the Interior
      - United States Housing Authority, 1938 - 1939 (Box 62, Folder 18)
        Correspondence and reports - Inner South End District of Boston, MA and housing areas of Chicopee, MA
      - Subsistence Homesteads, 1934 - 1935 (Box 62, Folder 19)
        Correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, maps, plans, reports -Subsistence Homesteads and low-cost housing
      - Subsistence Homesteads, 1934 (Box 62, Folder 20)
        **Note at top of folder labels contents as 'Confidential'** Correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, maps, plans, reports
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Accounts - Penderlea, North Carolina, 1934 - 1935 (Box 62, Folder 21)
        Correspondence - payment for services rendered at Penderlea Homesteads in Pender County, NC
      - U.S. Department of Commerce Committee - Industrial Decentralization, 1931 - 1933 (Box 62, Folder 22)
        Correspondence - Committee on Industrial Decentralization and Housing, the President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership
      - U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1932 - 1933 (Box 65, Folder 17)
        Correspondence, meeting minutes, reports - U.S. Chamber of Commerce; National Recover Act; Industrial Recovery Act; Agricultural Adjustment Act; Emergency Planning Bureau; Civic Development Committee and Nolen's role in this committee; Public Works Program; economic recovery; recovery efforts for construction industry
      - Miscellaneous Pamphlets, 1934 - 1935 (Box 67, Folder 9)
        Subsistence housing, rural electrification, New Deal programs
      - Subsistence Homesteads, 1933 - 1934 (Box 67, Folder 10)
        Bulletins, reports, reference lists
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Press Releases, June - December 1934 (Box 67, Folder 11)
        Department of the Interior Memorandum for the Press
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Press Releases, January - May 1934 (Box 67, Folder 12)
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Press Releases, September - December 1933 (Box 67, Folder 13)
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Press Releases, January - May 1935 (Box 67, Folder 14)
      - Homestead Houses (Box 67, Folder 15)
        2 copies of Booklet, "Homestead Houses: A Collection of Plans and Perspectives Issued by the Division of Subsistence Homesteads of the United States Department of the Interior"
      - Project Estimate Forms, 1934 (Box 67, Folder 16)
        Sample formd (blank) for US Department of the Interior, Division of Subsistence Homesteads - Form SH-B10 and Form SH-B11
      - Subsistence Homesteads - Outline of Studies (Box 67, Folder 17)
        Sample form (blank) for Subsistence Homestead projects
      - National Resources Board, May - December 1934 (Box 68, Folder 1)
        Reports - city,regional,state and land planning; administrative issues of National Resources Board
      - National Resources Board, January - June 1935 (Box 68, Folder 2)
        Bulletins, press releases, reports - replacement of National Resources Board with National Resources Committee in June 1935; national and state planning; public works planning; land use planning; planning legislation
      - National Resources Committee, July - December 1935 (Box 68, Folder 3)
        Bulletins, press releases, reports - state and regional planning; Works Progress Administration; statistical, survey, and research projects
      - National Resources Committee - Press Releases, January - June 1935 (Box 68, Folder 4)
        Reports and projects of National Resources Committee - Executive Order for creation of National Resources Committee; national water resources; surveying and mapping of US; mineral industries;new methods for land development
      - National Resources Committee - Press Releases, October - December 1935 (Box 68, Folder 5)
        Reports and projects of National Resources Committee - regional factors in national planning; State Planning Boards; educational situation; social and economic trends; provision of low-cost electric power for communities nationally; state populations
      - National Resources Committee - Circular IX, February 29, 1936 (Box 68, Folder 6)
        3 copies of Circular IX: Current Programs and Progress of Work for State Planning Boards
      - National Resources Committee - Press Releases, February - May 1936 (Box 68, Folder 7)
        Reports and projects of National Resources Committee - wildlife resources; "National Water Plan;" agriculture; major drainage basins; Federal corporate power agency in Columbia Basin, Pacific Northwest
      - National Resources Committee - Report Forms, 1936 (Box 68, Folder 8)
        Sample report forms - State Planning Activities; Urban Communities and Regions
      - National Resources Committee, January - March 1936 (Box 68, Folder 9)
        Bulletins, memorandum - administrative issues, water resources
      - National Resources Committee, April 1936 (Box 68, Folder 10)
        Bulletins, correspondence - administrative issues, state planning, Richmond Planning Conference, water resources
      - National Resources Committee, May 1936 (Box 68, Folder 11)
        Bulletins, correspondence, reports - administrative issues, water resources, industrial resources, state and regional planning
      - National Resources Committee, June 1936 (Box 68, Folder 12)
        Bulletins, reports - water resources; city, county and metropolitan planning
      - National Resources Committee, July - December 1936 (Box 68, Folder 13)
        Bulletins, reports - administrative issues, state planning boards, water resources, analysis of American Indian land
      - National Resources Committee, January - February 1937 (Box 68, Folder 14)
        Bulletins - administrative issues, water resources, roadside improvement
      - Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works - National Planning Board, 1933 - 1934 (Box 68, Folder 15)
        Circular letters, reports - administrative issues; city, regional, state planning; large scale regional and rural land planning; National Conference on City Planning and the American Civic Association
      - U.S. Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works, 1933 - 1936 (Box 68, Folder 16)
        Bulletins, PWA Forms, press releases - administrative issues, National Industrial Recovery Act, Housing Division, PWA's slum clearance and low-cost housing program, PWA Techwood project
      - U.S. Federal Housing Administration, 1935 - 1936 (Box 68, Folder 17)
        Bulletins, reports, speeches, press releases - National Housing Act; large scale and neighborhood housing; Better Housing Program; Federal Housing Program; revival of building industry
      - U.S. Federal Housing Administration, 1934 (Box 68, Folder 18)
        Press releases, speeches, reports - National Housing Act; Modernization Credit Plan; Better Housing Program; New Home Construction Program; revival of building industry
      - U.S. Public Works Administration - Housing Division, 1933 - 1936 (Box 68, Folder 19)
        Press releases, speeches, reports - administrative issues of Housing Division; mayoral roles in economic recovery; housing projects; meeting minutes of city planning consultants
      - U.S. Works Progress Administration - National Youth Administration, 1935 (Box 68, Folder 20)
        Bulletins, reports - administrative issues; work relief for unemployed youth; NYA Student Aid Program
      - U.S. Resettlement Administration, 1935 - 1936 (Box 68, Folder 21)
        Booklets, speeches, reports, press releases - land resettlement and development; R.G. Tugwell, Administrator of Resettlement Administration
      - Large Scale Regional and Rural Land Planning, 1933 (Box 70, Folder 24)
        Correspondence, meeting reports, speeches - American City Planning Institute's Committee on Rural Planning and Zoning; large scale planning
      - Welfare Council, 1932 - 1933 (Box 73, Folder 9)
        Housing Information Bureau Monthly Newsletters; Correspondence, pamphlets - Walter Kruesi, housing economist; Alice Flexner Rothblatt, Housing Section, Welfare Council of NYC; Brooklyn Garden Apartments; New York Housing Law
      - National Municipal League, 1923 - 1933 (Box 73, Folder 20)
        Correspondence - administrative affairs
      - Planning Foundation of America, 1931 - 1933 (Box 73, Folder 23)
        Correspondence - administrative issues; Foundation Bulletins "Planning Broadcasts" for 1931 and 1932
      - U.S. Chamber of Commerce, 1933 - 1936 (Box 73, Folder 26)
        Correspondence, pamphlets, reports - annual meetings; National Emergency Council; city planning; Public Works Program; housing issues in 1930s
      - Southeastern Planning Conference, 1936 (Box 73, Folder 28)
        Correspondence, reports - conference proceedings; National Resources Committee; Argiculture-Forestry Program for Southeastern States
      - Slum Clearance Conference, 1933 - 1934 (Box 73, Folder 29)
        Correspondence - conference program; Slum Clearance Committee of New York, R.H. Shreve, Director; State Housing Board; National Slum Clearance Conference in Cleveland
      - National Recreation Association, 1930 - 1936 (Box 73, Folder 30)
        Correspondence, pamphlets, reports - National Recreation Congress gatherings in Chicago, D.C., New England, Los Angeles; role of recreation in city planning
      - Public Housing Conference, 1933 - 1936 (Box 73, Folder 31)
        Correspondence - annual meetings; area conferences; Captain Richard L. Reiss, English Housing expert; public housing in Europe; national housing legislation
      - International Conference of Local Authorities, 1932 - 1934 (Box 74, Folder 1)
        Correspondence - Virginia state planning roundtable; Public Administration Clearinghouse; International City Managers' Association; 1932 London conference
      - Playground and Recreation Association, 1922 - 1924 (Box 75, Folder 43)
        Correspondence, pamphlets - Recreation Congress; recreation problems in city planning
      - Conference on Research and Instruction in City Planning, 1928 (Box 77, Folder 30)
        Correspondence - City Planning conference at Columbia University; Regional Plan of New York and its Environs
      - Migration of Industry Conference, 1928 (Box 77, Folder 31)
        Correspondence, report - conference proceedings
      - Lectures, 1916, 1932 (Box 88, Folder 7)
        "Industrial Housing" Address by John Nolen at Fifth National Conference on Housing in America, Providence, RI; "City Planning and the Community," by Justin R. Hartzog at Harvard School of Education
      - Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works - National Planning Board - Circular Letters, 1933 - 1934 (Box 88)
        Binder. City and regional planning, state planning, national planning, legislation, federal assistance, progress reports
      - National Resource Board, 1934 - 1935 (Box 98, Folder 5)
        Daily reports of activities, by Philip Shutler, Associate Consultant
      - National Resource Committee, June - December 1935 (Box 98, Folder 6)
      - National Resource Committee - Daily Report, January - March 1936 (Box 98, Folder 7)
      - National Committee on Community Organization, 1920 (Box 98, Folder 14)
        Correspondence, pamphlet - national conference, survey of status of community organizations nationally
      - City Planning Progress, 1909 - 1927 (Box 100, Folder 11)
        Writings; reports, reference lists, statistics - "Twenty Years of City Planning Progress in the United States," by John Nolen at National Conference on City Planning; city planning by state and city; city planning education
      - U.S. Housing Corporation, 1918 (Box 100, Folder 16)
        Blueprints, maps, lists - war time housing developments
      - Papers: National Conference on City Planning, 1912 - 1913 (Box 101, Folder 8)
        Correspondence, pamphlets, reports, maps - study in city planning
      - National Conference on City Planning, 1927 (Box 101, Folder 11)
        Correspondence, pamphlets, maps - administrative affairs, conferences, events, meetings
- Series V. Material About Nolen
  - The New City Foundations, 1991 (Box 41)
    Book. University of Miami School of Architecture
  - Runover CD Numbers 1-14 (Box 238, Folder 1A)
    plastic slides in boxes
  - Runover CD Numbers 15-27 (Box 238, Folder 1B)
  - Runover CD Numbers 28-63 (Box 238, Folder 1C)
  - Nolen CD Late (1,2,5) Numbers 1-40 (Box 238, Folder 2A)
  - Nolen CD Late (1,2,5) Numbers 41-80 (Box 238, Folder 2B)
  - Photographs from Negatives of Madison, WI, Kingsport, TN; East Bridgeport, CT; Walpole, MA; Mariemont, OH; Venice, FL; San Diego, CA; Reading, PA (Box 238)
    Photo CD. Photographs in Folder
  - Nolen for CD Mixed (3,6,7,8) Numbers 1-40 (Box 238)
  - Nolen for CD Mixed (3,6,7,8) Numbers 41-80 (Box 238)
  - Nolen for CD Mixed (3,6,7,8) Numbers 81-96 (Box 238)
  - Numbers 1-20 (Box 238)
    plastic slides in clear sleeve
  - "Survey of Photographic Materials in John Nolen Collection" by Janet T. Riemer and Cost Estimates of Archival Materials, 1992 (Box 240)
    report
  - "Far Above: Views of a 21st Century Library" Cornell University Library vol 2 No 1 Spring/Summer 1993, 1993 (Box 240)
    newsletter
  - West Palm Beach Master Plan, 1993 (Box 240)
    planning notes, maps, plans, charts, and photos
  - "West Plam Beach Charrette April 21-26, 1993 Design Team Manual" Duany Plater-Zyberk Architects and Town Planners, 1993 (Box 240)
  - "Expanding Demands on Planning: In what way can cooperation between experts, politicians, entrepreneurs and citizens lead to effective planning action? Case Studies" 30th International Congress, Prague, Czech Republic, 4-10 September 1994. Published by International Society of City and Regional Planners, 1994 (Box 240)
  - John Nolen: A Bibliographical Record of Achievement by John L. Hancock, Program in Urban and Regional Studies, Cornell University Ithaca, NY, September 1976 (Box 240)
    bound book
  - 15 slides of various plans, April 19, 1995 (Box 240)
    plastic slides
  - "John Nolen: New Towns in Florida" Reprinted from The New City University of Miami School of Architecture, Princeton Architectural Press, #1, Fall 1991, Fall 1991 (Box 240)
    bound book of pages from journal and correspondence regarding printing
  - "John Nolen and the Planning Archives at Cornell" documentation newsletter Department of Manuscripts and University Archives Cornell University,Volume XVI, No.1, Spring 1990 (Box 240)
  - American Town Plans: A Comparative Time Line by Keller Easterling (Box 240)
    book
  - American Town Plans: A Comparative Time Line by Keller Easterling HyperCard stack (Box 240)
    3.5" Floppy Disc
  - 10 copies of "Nolen in the 90s: A Symposium Examining the Modern-Day Relevance of John Nolen's Classic Urban Designs" presented by State Historical Society of Wisconsin (Box 240)
  - "Reviving Town Planning Principles in Practice: A Comparative Study of the Early 20th Century Work of John Nolen and the Current Work of Andres Duany & Elizabeth Plater-Zyberk Within a Larger Tradition of Town Planning" by Thomas Low (Box 240)
    study correspondence and outline
  - Images of Edison & Ford Winter Estates: Walker / Nolen Plan: Edison Pergola, CD-80
    CD-ROM
  - Nolen in the '90s "The New Urbanism's Relationship to the Nolen Era", V-357
    VHS Cassette
  - Nolen in the '90s "The State's Vision for Metropolitan Communities and It's Capital City", V-358
  - Nolen in the '90s "John Nolen's Vision for Madison / The Progressive ERA Town", V-359
  - Nolen in the '90s "The Public Realm and the Common Good", V-360
  - Nolen in the '90s "Compilation Video", V-361
  - Nolen in the '90s "The New Urbanism: Community of the Future or Niche Market", V-362